Hello and welcome back. One of the fun things of this week is
[未完成版本]欢迎回来 这周课程有趣在于
that we are learning a lot of background material.
我们将学到很多背景知识
While the background material is important for image processing, it's
这些背景材料不仅在图象处理中十分重要
important for many other disciplines. For example, in the previous video we
它们在很多其它学科中也有重要地位
learned about level sets. Level sets are important in image
譬如之前学过的水平集方法
processing to the curve evolution like active contours as we have seen numerous
它在像活动轮廓这样的曲线演化算法中有重要作用
examples last week. We saw a few this week and we are going
我们这周已经看到了一些例子
to see more even in the next coming videos.
在接下来还将见到更多
Another topic that is very important in mathematics and is also important in
另外一个在数学和图像处理上都很重要的
image processing is the calculus of variations.
工具是变分法
And that's what we're going to be talking right now in this video.
我们就要讲一讲它
And then in the next video we're going to see an example of that for image
在下一个视频我们将看到它的一个
denoiseing and image enhancement. So what is calculus of variations?
在图像降噪 图像增强方面的应用 那么什么是变分法
The idea is very simple, because it's an extension of finding extrema of
基本思想很简单 就是扩展求函数极值的方法
functions. But now we are going to be finding
但我们现在要求的是泛函的极值
extrema of functionals. And what do I mean by that?
这是什么意思
We're going to have images like you. And.
这是用u表示的图像
It's derivatives. So this is going to be an image for us.
和它的导数 那么u是一幅图像
And we're going to be looking at minimizing a function of the image.
我们将试图最小化一个关于图像的泛函
Might be the image is square, might be the gradient of the image, might be the
可能是图像函数的平方 可能是它的梯度
Laplacian of the image. So we're going to be trying to find
可能是它的拉普拉斯梯度 我们将求解出
what's the image that minimizes that function in the same way that we tried to
最小化这个函数的图像 正如我们
find, what's the point that minimizes a given function.
求解最小化给定函数的点一样
For example, if I draw this function then you say oh, this is the point that
譬如我画的这个函数 可见这是那个
minimizes it. But here, U is by itself what we are
最小化它的点 但这里 u这个函数是我们所求的
looking for. So we are not looking for a coordinate,
所以我们不是求一个坐标
we are looking for a function that minimizes this.
我们要求一个使这取极小值的函数
This is going to be very clear even in the next slide with an example.
通过下页的例子我们可以看得更明白
And we are going to make all the connection of the minimization of
我们给出求泛函极小值
function X with the minimization of functions.
和求函数极小值间的关系
Now, we're going to discuss in a couple of minutes that a condition for U to be a
我们要花几分钟说下 要使它取极小值
minimizer of this is to hold. This equation which is called the
u要令这个等式成立
Euler-Lagrange equation and this is the type of partial differential equation
这被称为欧拉-拉格朗日方程 它是我们在图像处理中
that we are going to be solving in image processing.
要使用的偏微分方程
Let me illustrate a bit more about this and then how we came to this equation
我们要演示下泛函是什么
which is completely parallel to the minimization of regular functions that we
以及我们怎么得出这个与传统微积分中
are away from regular standards in calculus.
求极值方法相似的方程的
So let's just illustrate, first of all, what do I mean by a functional.
首先 泛函是什么
Let's assume that I'm giving two points. And I am asking you what's the curve
给定两点 我问
connecting these two points that has the minimum length.
什么曲线穿过这两点而长度最短
So I am asking you for the function of that curve, the minimizer is going to be
那么我问的是曲线的函数 变量是一个函数
a function, not a point. The length of.
而不是一个点
Any curve, absolutely. Any curve connecting these two points is
任意过此两点的曲线的长度计算公式写在了这里
basically written here. The curve is parameterized as X Ux, we
曲线用x和u(x)表示 如我们所知
know about that, that's the particular case of that parameterization for
这是曲线的众多参数化表示的一种
basically any curve that goes. And connect those points.
适用于所有经过这两点的曲线
the length is. As we know, the derivative of the first
它的长度 如我们所知
coordinate squared so that's one squared derivative of the second coordinate
这是第一个坐标的导数的平方 这是第二个的
squared. So it's this function that we are going
所以这就是我们试图最优化的函数
to try to optimize. We already know what a function that
我们知道连接两点
minimizes the length between two points. It's a straight line.
距离最短的曲线是直线
But let's see how we get that. You see calculus offers variations, so
但让我们用变分法得出这个结果
I'm trying to find U connecting these two points.
要求得是过这两点的函数u
This is the condition for a function to be a minimizer of this function.
这是使所求形式的泛函取极小值所必须满足条件
So it's that integral over a function of functions.
也就是对一个函数的函数的积分这样的泛函
We haven't arrived at it yet, but we're going to discuss it in a few slides that
我们将在之后讨论这是如何得到的
this is what happened. So F is square root of one plus UX
这里 F是1加上ux的平方的开根
squared. So if you just do the numbers and takes,
如果你自己算一下
you take this and do the derivative according to U minus the derivative that
把这个带进来 求关于u的偏导 再减去这个导数
is written here, you get this expression. So this expression is nothing else than
结果就是它 所以这个结果就是
applying this to f as written here. Now this equal to zero is a condition for
把上面的F带入所得的
the particular U we are looking for to solve the problem that we are searching
它等于0是u为所求的必要条件
for, meaning the minimizer of the length connecting these two points.
也就是能最小化过这两点距离的曲线
Now we have this equals zero, the denominator doesn't matter.
令它为0 分母不重要
In when we have eight over B equal zero when its to be equal zero is U, so U
所以这里是u
double derivative equal zero, that means that the first derivative is constant and
u关于x的二阶导等于0 即一阶导是常数
then is that the function is 8X plus B that's a straight line.
所以函数是ax+b 一条直线
And A and B are found by what's called the boundary conditions.
确定a,b可以通过所谓的边界条件
We know that it has to go through these points.
我们知道它要穿过这些点
So if I replace here X by a zero, I have to get this point and if I replace by X
所以令x=0 得到这个点
one, I have to get this point and in that way, I get A and B.
令x=1 得到那个点 同理可得a和b
So we see that for length, the function that basically solves the Euler-Lagrange,
所以对长度来说 符合欧拉方程(必要条件)的解
and that's a necessary condition, is a straight line.
就是条直线
So basically, if we take this curve here, it will have certain length.
所以如果取这条曲线 它有一定长度
But actually, the one that minimizes is not this because this is not a straight
但它不是长度最小的那条 它不是直线
line. The one that minimizes is this one.
能最小化长度的是这条
So, a function to be a minimizer has to haul the Euler-Larange equation.
所以一个能使泛函取极小值的函数必须满足欧拉方程
Why is that important, and how do we get to the Euler-Lagrange equation?
这有什么用 欧拉-拉格朗日方程又是怎么来的
Let us go for a second back to regular functions, and how we find the minima of
让我们回顾下求常规函数的极小值点的方法
a regular function. So you might not remember exactly how we
[未完成版本] 你可能记不清楚具体是怎么做的了
do that. But you do remember the result, which is
但你应该记得这个结果
going to explain next. The basic idea is, you have a function.
核心思想是 给定一个函数
And you have the function around a certain point.
给定一个围绕某个点的函数
And you do a small perturbation of that function.
然后在该点处取一个微小增量
And you take the derivative according to that perturbation.
再求关于这个增量的导数
And the condition for a point to be a maximum or a minimum is that when you do
那么这点为极值点的必要条件就是
any perturbation, the derivative is equal to zero.
对任意增量 导数为0
If you compute the derivative according to the permutation, you get this, and
如果你求关于增量的导数 结果是这个
this has to hold for every n. So the derivative of the function for
这对于每个n都要成立 所以函数关于任何n的导数
every end has to be equal zero which means that this has to be zero, and we
都要是0 也就是这个是0
know that. We know that the condition of a point to
所以某点是极值点的必要条件
be an extreme of a function is that it's derivative have to be equal to zero.
就是这个导数为0
Now why is that so important? We know that but why is that so
这有什么用 我们知道它能有什么用
important? Because then I can write this
由它我可以写下这个微分方程
differential equation. Xt so I can make X change in the
Xt 也就是我能让x
direction of minus the derivative and that basically says that you start from a
沿使导数 也就是梯度值减小的方向变化 也就是从某点开始
point and your next point, because X is changing in time, it just, you move a bit
你的下一点 因为x在随时间变化
in the direction of the derivative of the function.
沿负梯度方向移动一点
Remember, derivative is tangent so you move a bit to the next spot.
记得这是相切的 移动一点得到下一个点
This is how you move. Your next point is this point minus a
这就是移动的方法 下一个点是这个点减去
tiny step in the direction of the derivative.
一个在梯度方向上很小的一步
That's what this equation is telling us. Because if we were to discretize this
这就是这个式子的意思 因为如果把它离散化
equation, we get that, that. X.
我们有 x
We just saw the result there. We had the X at T plus Delta T minus X at
如那里的结果 有x(t+dt)-x(t)
T. Divided by delta T, that's a [INAUDIBLE]
再除以dt 这就是它的离散化
equation of this. This expression is equal to minus fx and
这等于-fx
that's what we have here so we go slowly. In the direction of the derivative of X
也就是这个式子 因此我们沿着负梯度方向慢慢的移动x
until we get to this point. Let's just see that again.
直到到达这一点 再看一次
We go one step and then we will go another step and another step until
走一步 再走一步 再一步
basically we get to the steady state. In the steady state, we have the XT
直到稳态附近 在稳态处 xt=0
equals zero. Nothing is changing anymore and,
什么就都不变化了
therefore, this. Is = to zero, which is our condition.
因此它等于0 也就是我们的条件
So once again, we know that the condition for a point to be a minimal of a
再说一次 我们知道一个点是极小值点的条件
function. Is it has to be the derivative = to zero.
是函数在该点的导数为0
So we take a point. I'm going to just show that to you again
那么取一个点 再演示一遍
We take a point and we move it in the direction of the derivative and then
取一个点 沿负梯度方向移动
slowly we are moving it in the direction of the derivative and we are moving it
缓慢地移动它一次又一次
again until it doesn't move anymore. When it doesn't move anymore.
直到它不能再动为止
This is equal to zero, which is the condition for it to be a minimum.
此时它为0 也就是取极值的必要条件
So we arrive to a point that is in this case a minimum.
在这个例子里 我们就求得了一个极小值点
So this concept extends to functionals, in the same fashion.
把这种方法同样延伸到泛函上
Very simple again. We start from a functional, and then
很简单还是 从一个泛函开始
we're going to ask u to be in extrema, so we do a perturbation.
想要令u使泛函取极值 给u一个增量
So, u is here, the yellow curve. It's basically our original function now.
u是这条黄色曲线 就是我们的初始曲线
We do a perturbation. Now, the perturbation, now, is another
给一个增量 现在增量是另一个函数
function. Because we're not talking about points.
因为这些不是点
We're talking about entire functions. So this is the perturbation.
它们都是函数了 这就是那个增量
And then u tilda is the sum of my function and the perturbation.
u~ 是原来的u和增量的和
And what I want is when I replace U by U tilde, I replace it by the perturbation
我们想用u~代替u
and I take the derivative, according to the perturbation, has to be equal to
然后求泛函关于扰动的导数(变分)
zero, the same way than when I did the point perturbation for functions, I got
它必须是0 跟普通函数的情况一样
zero. If I do a function perturbation here, I
如果我施加一个函数增量这里
have to get zero. From this, after a few lines of just
它也应该是0 由此 经过几步求导运算
taking derivatives, we get the Euler-Lagrange equation.
就得到欧拉-拉格朗日方程
So that's how we get basically the
这就是如何利用增量函数
Doing the derivative according to the [INAUDIBLE] that we are using.
求得欧拉-拉格朗日方程的过程
Once you have basically the Euler-Lagrange equation, you can do the
得到了欧拉-拉格朗日方程后
same that we did for functions. You can move your function in the
就可以做之前用在函数上的事了 你可以移动你的函数
direction of the Euler-Lagrange equation until steady state,
沿着欧拉-拉格朗日方程规定的方向直到稳态
when you get to state, you have solved your Euler-Lagrange equation.
当到达稳态时 你就求得了欧拉-拉格朗日方程的一个解
So let's just illustrate that here. Look what happened.
在这里演示下
I want to put that, basically. I want to do that again,
我想重新再做一次
okay? So you're going to basically move until
基本上你要一直移动它
you get to the steady state. When you get to steady state, basically
直到稳定下来 当它稳定了
we've got zero. So let us recap what we just saw.
变分就是0了 让我们重新看下这件事
In regular calculus, we basically are moving a point, not a curve, removing a
在常规的微积分里 我们移动点而不是曲线
point in the direction of minus the derivative and basically we get, the
沿着负梯度方向移动点
solution which is the minima. In the case of the calculus of
就求得了极小值点 在变分法中
variations, we move, we move the function in the direction of the Euler-Lagrange
我们移动函数 沿着欧拉-拉格朗日方程规定的方向
basically again the derivative for the perturbation.
也就是泛函关于增量的导数方向
We do that all the way to stay state, okay?
如此直到稳定 明白了么
And just do that again. We do it all the way to steady state and
再来一遍 一直那么做直到稳定
at the point of steady state basically this became zero.
然后稳定时 这就成了0
And we have solved the Euler-Lagrange which is the condition, basically, for
于是求得了欧拉-拉格朗日方程的一个解
getting an extreme amount in this case a minima.
也就是满足了取极值 这里取极小值的必要条件
We can change the signs and get the maxima.
改变符号我们就能求极大值点
So we are going to see, in the next video, how we can take you to be an
在下一个视频里 我们将用u表示一幅图像
image. We'll do some interesting function of F.
令F取一些有意思的函数
And get, for example. Blurring the image or get image noisy.
得到 譬如模糊或加了噪声的图像
So once again, our unknown is the image that basically optimizes this function.
总的来说 这里未知的是能优化这个函数的图像
And we get the complete analogy between regular calculus and calculus of
我们在常规的微积分和变分法间得到了一个类比
variations and as I say for [INAUDIBLE] and even more for calculus of variations,
这些像水平集方法 变分法的技术
these type of techniques go way beyond image processing.
如我所说 应用远超过了图像处理
What image processing did, and in particular the area of partial
而图像处理所做的 在偏微分方程领域
differential equations, is to borrow these techniques from continuous
就是把这些连续数学里的方法
mathematics into this area. Once again, I'm going to show you in the
借用过来 下个视频里
next video an example of a function that is very useful for image processing.
我将讲讲一个在图像处理方面非常有用的函数
I see you in the next video. Thank you very much.
[未完成版本] 下个视频再见 谢谢